本影音版权属其出版、发行方，字幕制作仅供学术交流之用 请于下载后24小时内删除，并不得有公开传播或作商业盈利之行为 若有违法等相关行为，诸神字幕组恕不承担任何法律或连带责任。
翻译 koki  放 晴  La Fatalité
压制 暗之亚瑟王  校对 凉YAN Lucifer 时间 Lucifer
Ismo Republic, Fulbeck City.
イスモ共和国　フルベック　文化と芸術の都
The capital of art and culture.
Cinematic actress, Parny Pealrmanta.
シネマの女優　パーニィ＝パールマンタ
Eight years ago, she was
murdered in this very town.
彼女は八年前　この町で殺された
She was pursuing Lascall Othello.
彼女はラスコール＝オセロを追っていた
止まる者　愚かなりし
The one who stops is foolish
はらりひらり指に触れた黒い翼の　一片
A piece of black wing gently touches fingers
诸
神&动漫国
君が一つの　物語なら
If you were a story
まだいくらでも　掛け替えられる
You could still rewrite it all you want
血のインクは乾かない
The ink of blood doesn't dry up
誰も知らない　本との僕ら
No one knows the real us
荒れた世界　枯れるのは
What changes the chaotic world
追い求めたのは　ちっぽけな幸福なんかじゃない
What we pursued isn't
Small happiness
戦え　轟く　音を合図に
Fight with a rumbling heartbeat as a sign
意のまま　進めば
What awaits you is infinite if you
move forward as you wish
行く先　果てない
抗え　のたうち
Fight off no matter how many
times you get defeated
幾度と　汚れと
Engrave your dream onto the scar you bear
膝を纏った傷跡に夢を
埋もれそうな今日の記憶繋げるために　明日へ
In order to connect today's memory that's
on the verge of being buried to tomorrow
Episode 13
A Day Off, a Picture Book, and Rusty Hair
第13话 休假
与
画册
和
锈红色之发
I wonder if that's another murder.
また　殺しかな
Huh?
え？
That serial killer.
連続殺人ってやつです
There's no connection between the victims.
被害者に接点はなし　犯人の見当も付いていません
We have no idea who's behind the attacks.
Sorry to bother you at such a busy time.
お忙しいところを　恐縮です
She was cut straight through the bone.
骨まで一直線に切断されていました
One must assume he's a magic user.
魔法を使う者の犯行でしょう
その事件は未だに謎ばかりでしたね
It's one giant mystery.
Why are you looking into the
Parny murder, though?
しかし　なぜ今になってパーニィ事件を？
Oh, that's for a separate investigation.
あっ　別件の調査の関連です
They said she was pursuing Lascall Othello?
彼女はラスコール＝オセロを追っていたそうですが
Lascall Othello...
ラスコール＝オセロ　御伽話に出てくる魔法使い
A sorcerer from a fairy tale...
When girls die, having never told
the person they love their feelings,
恋する少女が思いを伝えられずに　命を落としたとき
he delivers their Books to their beloved.
その「本」を思い人へ届けるという
八年前　この町でラスコール＝オセロが実在し
Eight years ago, a rumor spread through
town that Lascall Othello actually exists,
死んだ後　望む相手に「本」を届けてもらえる
and upon people's deaths,
he takes their Books to their loved ones.
そんな噂が立ちました
There were some con artists pretending
either to be Lascall himself
ラスコールを名乗る者　ラスコールに会わせてやると
or offering to introduce one
to him for a fee, right?
金品を騙し取る者まで現れたそうですね
Armed Librarian Hiza Meeken,
事態を収拾するために　武装司書ハイザ＝ミッケンが派遣された
was dispatched to calm the situation.
Yes.
はい　調査の結果
According to the investigation,
Parny was the source of the rumors.
パーニィが噂の出所だと判明しました
Using Hiza's Book, we confirmed the matter.
事情はハイザの「本」で確認しました
He exists...
いるのよ　ラスコール＝オセロは本当にいるの
Lascall Othello really exists.
Will he carry my Book for me?
私の「本」を運んでくれるの
Do you know? Do you know where Lascall is?
あなた知らない？　ラスコールがどこいるか　会いたい
I must see him.
ねー
Please!
Afterwards,
その後　当時のフォトナ館長代行がラスコールは実在しないと正式に発表し
Acting Director Fotona made a formal
announcement of Lascall's nonexistence...
噂もすぐに忘れさられたそうですが
It quickly put an end to the rumors.
Exactly. He said they were nothing
but the ramblings of drunks.
そうだったわね
酔っ払いの戯言に振り回されていたってわけよ
But was that really true?
本当にそうだったのでしょうか
What are you getting at?
どういうこと？
Why would someone proclaim such
absurdities simply due to drunkenness?
酔っているからと言って
そんな荒唐無稽なことをいうものでしょうか
Parny was murdered right
after Hiza arrived in town.
ハイザが尋ねた直後　パーニィは殺されています
I feel there's more to the story.
何か　気になるんです
Lascall Othello?
ラスコール＝オセロ？
Yes.
はい　ウインケニーはハイザの「本」を狙っていました
Winkeny was after Hiza's Book.
Hiza was after Lascall.
ハイザはラスコールを追っていた
何か関係あるのでは？
What if the two were connected?
So?
それで？
Please allow me to look into it!
私に調べさせてください
A sorcerer who delivers the
Books of girls in love...
恋する乙女の「本」を運ぶ魔法使いか
I never took you as one of the
little girls who buy into all that.
君はそこまで少女趣味とは知らなかった
What about Colio Tonies having
three fragments of Shiron's Book?
コリオ＝トニスがシロンの「本」を三度も手に入れた件は
Is that mere coincidence?
あれが偶然でしょうか？
I'm not saying that Lascall is real.
ラスコールは実在するとは言いません
But what if there's someone with the ability
to gather Books, just like in the legend?
しかし　伝説と同じように「本」を集める能力を持つ者がいるとしたら
神溺教団に関わった者の「本」が出て来ないことにも説明がつきます
It would also account for the fact that we
rarely find the Books of Church members.
Are you serious?
本気か？
One more thing.
もうひとつ
There's a legend that says
if you pursue him, you'll die.
ラスコールを追った者には死が訪れるという伝説もあるそうです
Hiza, Parny, Winkeny...
ハイザ　パーニィ　ウインケニー
Milepoc.
ミレポ
I'm the one who killed Hiza and Winkeny, dear.
ハイザとウインケニーを殺したのはわーたーし
Th-That's certainly true, but...
そ、それはそうですが
It's not often we see you so fired up.
珍しいじゃない　熱くなちゃって
What's the matter, Milepoc?
どうしたのかな　ミレポ
I'm not fired up!
熱くなんてなっていません
I'm just...
ただ…
Just?
ただ？
People's deaths are to be mourned.
人の死は悲しまなければならない
The ability to save people should be celebrated.
救えることを喜ばなくては…
奪われた命に少しでも疑念があるのなら
If any suspicion surrounds someone's death,
is it not our duty, as Armed Librarians,
それを解明することが我々武装司書の使命ではないでしょうか？
to investigate?
Funny you should mention it...
そういえば　昨日少年が一人同じ話を聞きに来ました
Yesterday, a young boy came by,
asking the same questions.
He appeared to be researching
Lascall Othello.
ラスコール＝オセロについて調べているようでしたが
A boy?
少年？
He looked about ten years old.
十歳ぐらいの子でしたか？　もちろん何も教えませんでしたが
I didn't tell him anything, of course.
Who else would be looking into this?
私のほかに　一体誰か？
Miss.
あのう…
Pardon us...
失礼ですが
Yes?
あっ　はい
Wh-Wh-What the heck?
こ、これは一体？
It looks great on you!
よくお似合いですよ
I was asked to find the woman in military
fatigues and get her into a dress.
軍服の女性を見つけてドレスを見立てするようご依頼を受けまして
だ、誰にですか？
Wh-Who requested that?
Me.
俺だよ
Matt?!
マットさん
ほー　似合ってるじゃないか
Wow, you look fantastic.
Huh?
え？
Reminds me of the princesses
from my school plays.
学芸界のお姫様って感じだな
Military fatigues make you stand
out too much in this town.
この町で軍服じゃ目立ちすぎる
何かと不便だと思ったな
I figured that would be
to your disadvantage.
Thank you for your concern.
お気遣いありがとうございます
それで　どうしてここに？
Anyway, what are you doing here?
I have a day off, just like you.
休暇だ　お前と同じだよ
Did you come to spy on me?
監視ですか
I've got better things to do than that.
そこまで暇じゃない
Oh, so you are spying.
そうですか　監視ですか
Hey, now...
あのな…
So, how's the capital of art
and culture treating you?
どうだ？　芸術と文化の都は
Did you take in a film?
シネマは見たのか？
Nope.
いいえ
You don't like films?
シネマに興味は？
I don't care for the arts.
芸術に興味はありません
What a lonely life.
寂しい人生だな
何か？
What now?
Don't you want to see one of Parny's movies?
パーニィのシネマを見てないのか
They're doing a revival run now.
今リバイバルてやってるぞ
Huh?
Aren't you looking into her murder?
調べてるんだろう　あの事件を
I knew you were here to spy on me.
やっぱり監視していたんですね
Why go so far to look into it?
なぜそこまで拘る？
I already told you!
お話したはずです
Because it's your "duty as an Armed Librarian"?
武装司書の使命ってやつか
Is that really the only reason?
本当にそれだけなのか
What are you implying?
どういう意味ですか
Nothing.
別に
That's it. There's no other reason.
それだけです　ほかに意味なんて…
Please excuse me.
失礼します
A fired-up Milepoc, huh?
燃えるミレポか　どう思う？
What should we do?
Mattalast Balory.
マットアラスト＝バロリー
Milepoc Finedel.
ミレポック＝ファインデル
They've come for Parny's Book, too.
やつらもパーニィの「本」を狙ってる
Why do I carry this around?
私　どうしてこんなもの持ってるんだろう
ラスコール＝オセロは不思議な不思議な本屋さんです
Lascall Othello is a mysterious,
mysterious proprietor of Books.
He gathers Books with his mysterious
power and flies around the globe.
不思議な力で「本」を集め
不思議な力で世界を飛び回ります
Then, when girls die, having never told
the person they love their feelings,
そして　恋する少女が思いを伝えられず
命を落としたとき
he delivers their Books to their beloved.
その「本」を思い人へと届けてあげるのです
There are Armed Librarians in town?
武装司書がこの町に？
So they're the ones who killed
this town's False Men?
では　この間からこの町の「擬人」たちを殺しているのは彼らなの？
Why would they do such a thing?
なんでこんなことに
シガルやガンバンゼルのせいだ
It's all Cigal and Ganbanzel's fault!
They challenged Hamyuts Meseta
to that stupid fight!
ハミュッツ＝メセタに戦いなんて挑むから
How can they do this to True Men?
真なる人に向かってなんてことを
Get a grip! We've reported
this to headquarters.
落ち着け　本部には連絡してある
護衛の戦士が到着するのを待って…
We'll wait for security officers to come.
Wh-Who are you?
あ、あなたは？
Are you a soldier from the Church?
教団の戦士の方ですか？
This is great! Please save us!
よかった　助けてください
The Armed Librarians murdered our brothers!
武装司書が仲間を…
Where's Parny's Book?
パーニィの「本」はどこだ？
Huh? Parny?
パーニィ？
Do you mean Parny Pealrmanta?
パーニィ＝パールマンタのことか？
How the heck would we know?! Save us!
そんなもの知るか　助けてくれ
Oh, you don't know.
そうか　知らないのか
In that case, die!
ならば死ね
A red sword... Alme Noten!
赤い毛　アルメ＝ノートン
裏切り者のアルメ？
Alme, the traitor?
You people were speaking ill of
Master Cigal, were you not?
お前ら　シガル様を侮辱していたな
I will not allow anyone to insult Master Cigal.
シガル様を侮辱するやつは許さない
That goes for those who killed him, too!
シガル様を殺したやつらも
I'll kill them all...
殺せ
Hamyuts Meseta!
ハミュッツ＝メセタを
Mattalast Balory!
マットアラスト＝バロリーを
ミレポック＝ファインデルを
Milepoc Finedel!
And I'll kill Lascall Othello...
殺す　ラスコール＝オセロを
Oh, poor thing...
まぁ　可哀そうに
ラスコール＝オセロはそもそも我々とはありものが異なる存在
Beautiful...
美しい
The notes you play are replete
with frustration and rage.
君の奏でる音色は　苛立ちと怒りに満ちている
Master Cigal was killed.
シガル様が殺された　ラスコール＝オセロのせいだ
And it's Lascall Othello's fault.
It's because he gave Shiron's
Book to that human bomb!
やつがあの人間爆弾にシロンの「本」を渡したから
From the very beginning, Lascall Othello
has had a separate existence from ours.
He is not to be pursued,
under any circumstances.
決して追ってはならない　追う者には死　あるのみ
Those who pursue him face certain death.
Hiza's Book?
ハイザの「本」？
An order from the Governor of Paradise?
楽園管理者の命令か
モッカニアの専念させたてほしいだが
I'd rather he let me focus solely on Mokkania.
Oh, well...
仕方がない
Are you the one who spoke
ill of Master Cigal?
シガル様を侮辱したのはお前か
Or was it you?
それともお前か
Was it you?
お前か　お前か　お前か
Ah, I'll have to ask the front
desk to get this laundered.
フロントにクリーニングを頼まなきゃ
Be right there!
あっ　はい
Seems some people were murdered last night.
昨日の夜　殺人事件があったそうだ
このところ　続いているそうです
There's been a string of murders here.
俺は保安官事務所に行ってみる
I'll pay the police station a visit.
Understood.
分かりました
I'm going to see Keith Queen.
私はキース＝クリンのところに行ってみます
Keith Queen?
キース＝クリン？
The one who runs the illegal
Book-selling operation?
「本」の密売組織を取り仕切ってる　あいつか？
There's a rumor floating around that claims
Parny's Book is somewhere here in town.
パーニィの「本」はこの街のどこかにあるという噂が流れています
I think the best place to start would
be with the organized Book thieves.
You know what they use those
illegally sold Books for, right?
まずは盗本組織を探ってみるのが基本かと
密売されている「本」が何に使われているか　分かってるんだろうな
お、主に女性の「本」で　性的な興味のために使われていると
Typically, they use women's
Books for sexual purposes.
Porn.
ポルノだ
Sure you're ready for this mission on your own?
一人で行くのは早すぎるかな
I'm going!
行きます
I'll stop every last scumbag out there
committing these horrific crimes!
そんな破廉恥な犯罪を犯した者は全員拘束して来ます
Go easy on 'em.
お手柔らかに
What's that?
それは？
Honey.
蜂蜜です
For some reason,
I'm hooked on the stuff.
なんだか　癖なってしまって
Want some?
要りますか？
No, thank you.
いや　いい
Just to be safe, leave the
telepathic channel open.
念のため　思考は繋いだままにしておけ
Be ready to communicate on a moment's notice,
should anything happen. Okay?
何かあったらすぐ連絡するように　いいな
Understood.
分かりました
I'm also curious about a boy
who visited the police.
保安官の所に来たと言う少年のことも気になりますが
You got it. I'll ask the police about it.
ついでだ　俺は詳しく聞いて来よう
Thank you.
お願します
Keith Queen...
キース＝クリン
I've been waiting for you.
待っていたよ
He told me that Parny's Book isn't here.
ここにパーニィの「本」はないってさ
He didn't know a damn thing.
こいつも何も知らねぇって
Who are you?
あなたは？　神溺教団？
Are you with the Church?
What? Shoot me.
どうした？　撃てよ
Freeze!
動かないで　動いたら　撃つわ
Move and I'll shoot.
No dice, missy.
You can't kill me with that.
ダメだよ　お嬢ちゃん　それじゃ勝てない
You'll have to attack me personally.
自分から攻めて来ないと
何を？
What?
You've never killed someone before, have you?
お前　人を殺したことないだろう
Now, where were we?
さて　どうするかな
Matt!
マットさん
You all right, Milepoc?
無事か　ミレポ
はい
Yes...
There are police cordons
set up across town.
町中に非常線を張りそうだ
理由は分からんが　神溺教団が動いている
The Church is up to something,
but I don't know why.
At the least, we're certain
they're after Parny's Book.
少なくともパーニィの「本」を狙っているのは確かだな
Sorry to keep you waiting.
お待たせしました
パーニィ事件の資料ですが　見当たりませんね
Parny's case file...
I can't seem to find it.
What are you talking about?
どういうことだ？
Look, the case is eight years old.
さぁ　もう八年も前の事件ですし
It was probably already
boxed up and stored away.
どこかに紛失してしまったのか
You're lying!
嘘です
I saw it with my own eyes, yesterday!
昨日私は見ました
Heck, weren't you the one who showed me?
あなたが見せてくれたんじゃありませんか
Yesterday? Are you sure you aren't mistaken?
昨日？　何かの間違いでは？
I had never met you before today.
あなたに会うのは　今日は初めてですが
You're lying...
そんな
Fine! What about the boy who
came by to ask about Lascall?
では　ラスコールの話を聞きに来た少年のことは？
"Lascall"? What are you talking about?
ラスコール　一体なんですか？
He wasn't there when I arrived.
俺が来た時　彼はいなくてな
I wasn't able to ask about it.
話を聞けなかった
I'm telling the truth!
I saw the case file myself!
本当です　私は資料を見ましたし
He told me about the boy, too!
少年の話も本当に聞いたんです
分かってる　恐らくあの男は
I believe you.
The Church probably got him
to drink some water from Argax.
神溺教団の者にアーガックスの水を飲まされた
That's all it is.
それだけなことだ
Investigate that officer again!
あの保安官をもう一度調べましょう
We can't let the police know about the Church.
教団の存在を保安官たちに知らせるわけにはいかない
Besides, the Church isn't the type to
leave evidence lying around anyway.
それに調べたところで　証拠残すようなやつらじゃない
But!
しかし…
Calm down!
落ち着け　どうしたんだ　ミレポ
What's wrong with you, Milepoc?
You've been acting strange lately.
最近の君はおかしいぞ　冷静さを失っている
You've lost your composure.
That's not true.
そんなことはありません
Then why did you come here?
ではなぜこの町に来た
キースの屋敷に異変が気づいた時
Why didn't you contact me the second you
saw the dead body in Keith's mansion?
なぜすぐに連絡をしなかった
一人で何とかできるとでも思ったのか
Did you think you could go this alone?
I... I...
それは…
A fired-up Milepoc, huh?
燃えるミレポか　どう思う？
What should we do?
She's acting in haste.
あいつには　焦りがある
Her offensive powers are weaker
than most Armed Librarians.
他の者にくらべ　戦闘能力が低い
That may be weighing on her,
deep inside her heart.
そのことが　心の底で引っ掛ってるんだろう
Though I don't think she's
realized it herself...
もっとも　本人に自覚はないようだが
Also...
それに…
"People's deaths."
人の死を　救えることを　武装司書の使命
"The ability to save."
"Duty as an Armed Librarian."
なんだか　誰かさんみたいな口ぶりだったわねえ
She's starting to sound like
someone else we knew.
Now, who was that again?
誰だったかしら
Oh, yeah, that's right!
Little Mr. Volken.
あー　そうそう　ヴォルケン坊や
ミレポほどの「思考共有」の使い手はそういない
We have no one else who can
use telepathy at her level.
We can't afford to lose her right now.
今　あいつを失うわけにはいかない
But a fired-up Milepoc cannot be stopped.
でも　燃えるミレポは止められない
So what should we do?
どうする？
You've never killed someone before, have you?
お前　人を殺したことないだろう
She saw right through me,
見抜かれた　初めて会った相手に
even though we had never met before.
Damn.
くそ
Just awful.
下手くそ
I'm so happy, Master Cigal.
シガル様　アルメは幸福です
I'm but a lowly False Man,
serving a True Man.
「真人」にお使えする「擬人」の分際で
Is it right for me to feel this happy?
こんなに幸せてよいのでしょうか
Get out of here, you damned pig!
出て行け！　この豚め
Master Cigal?
シガル様
You're a useless piece of trash.
どうしようもないくずだ　殺すのも汚らわしい
It's not worth dirtying my hands to kill you.
Leave! Get out of my sight!
消えろ　消えせろ
Lascall Othello is a mysterious,
mysterious proprietor of Books.
ラスコール＝オセロは不思議な不思議な本屋さんです
He gathers Books with his mysterious
power and flies around the globe.
不思議な力で「本」を集め
不思議な力で世界を飛び回ります
What a wretched sound...
いやな音
Then, when girls die, having never told
the person they love their feelings,
そして　恋する少女が思いを伝えられず
命を落としたとき
he delivers their Books to their beloved.
その「本」を思い人へと届けてあげるのです
It appears the stage is set.
舞台は整ったようだ
So it would seem.
そのようで
あの二人　君に辿り着くことはできるかな
Do you think those two can reach you,
Lascall Othello?
ラスコール＝オセロ
Those girls are like precious gems.
宝石のような少女たちでございます
They just may be able to...
あるいは…
Lost the light
Before closing the sun
If it's a sparkling storm
Jump in before it tempts
The end comes to everyone one day
When the day comes
Aim for the future that begins to move
Even if it's already been written
Search and even acquire the
meaning of getting hurt
In order to be myself
The Setting Sun,
取るに足らない出会いと別れが
Meetings and farewells of no significance
flicker violently and crumble apart.
激しく瞬き弾け行く
The Setting Sun, a Storyteller,
flicker violently and crumble apart.
All of its meaningless twinkling,
その無意味な輝きは
目を閉じでもまだ
even when you close your eyes,
remains burned into your vision.
残像が残ってる
The Setting Sun, a Storyteller,
and a Collection of Fables
remains burned into your vision.
落日与往事和数个寓言